### Samuel Ferrer

ferraxi@gmail.com, Langevåg, Norway

### Summary

Hardworking software engineer offering wide-ranging expertise and more than 28 years of software industry experience. Background in testing, evaluating, designing and implementing solutions. Specializing in programming languages such as Python, C, C++, Java, Kotlin and JavaScript. Meticulous Software Engineer . In-depth understanding of web technologies with focus on delivering innovative business solutions.

Proactive, creative, positive and a team player who never gives up on the toughest situations.

### Active from September 1992 to present (28 years)

### Skills and Technologies

- Methodologies and Software Development Lifecycle Processes
  - Scrum
  - Agile
  - Test Driven Development
  - Rational Unified Process
- Technology Trends
  - Machine Learning
  - Cloud Computing (AWS)
  - Blockchain and Crypto currency
- Full Stack Developer
  - o .NET
  - Java
  - Mobile Applications (Android with Kotlin)
  - Node JS
  - LAMP
- Programming Languages and Frameworks
  - Java, Kotlin, Python, C, C++, PHP, Delphi, C#, Assembler, Visual Basic, Pascal, Fortran, Lua, VHDL, Ada. Matlab, Javascript

- .NET, Java Swing, Microsoft Presentation Foundation, Android, Enterprise Java Beans
- Databases
  - MySQL, MS SQL Server, Sybase, DB2, Progress, Vertica
- Architecture Styles
  - Multilayer architecture
  - Microservices
  - Highly distributed and decentralized architectures
  - Embedded systems
  - Grid computing based systems
- Bioinformatics
  - Pharmaceutics bioinformatics
  - Drug design
  - Genomic algorithms and applications
- Miscellaneous
  - Docker (Containerization technology)
  - Kubernetes (Container orchestration)
  - Terraform (Infrastructure as Code)
  - Business Intelligence (data visualization)
  - Git, Github, CodeCommit (Version Control System)
  - ABB Advant Controllers
  - Edge computing
  - AWS Comprehend
  - Blockchain

### Experience

**Full Stack Developer** Self employee, Norway

Sep, 2020 - Jan, 2021

- Full Stack developer consultant at TCS
- Maintenance of NETS payment system
- Development of tool in order to manage security certifications

**Client: NETS** 

Technologies: Java, Spring Boot, NodeJS, Service Now, Scrum

### **Developer Consultant**

Self employee, Norway

Jun 2021

- Designed and implemented *Lamda-Pipe* pattern design, own pipeline oriented pattern that easier the processes of verification and validation
- Functioned as advisor and guider about competitive

#### technologies

**Client**: HERNAT CONSULTING LIMITED

**Technologies**: AWS, AWS Lambda, AWS Comprehend NodeJS, Terraform

### **Lead Software Engineer**

Secintech, Sweden

Feb 2020 - May 2021

- Designed mobile applications for Android platform.
- Analyzed solutions and coding fixes for software problems.
- Worked closely with development team members to identify and remove software bugs.
- Installed, configured and executed server software.
- Advised customers and users on required maintenance practices for diverse software systems to support OEM warranty requirements and industry best practices.
- Optimized system performance by making proactive adjustments and resolving bugs.
- Directed all software design, architecture and programming.
- Implemented and tested enhancement feature requests to improve product functionality and extend performance.
- Conducted full life-cycle software development in multiple software environments.
- Refactored legacy code to drive system architecture improvement.
- Developed production, test and beta websites using various software programs.

**Technologies**: Linux, AWS, Android, Kotlin, NodeJS, Android CameraX and barcode scanning, HTML5, Java

#### **Senior Software Developer**

Senecta Innovation AB

Mar 2019 - Jan 2020

- Created proof-of-concept prototype applications for demonstration and evaluation purposes.
- Developed product and technology roadmap and strategy from concept to launch.
- Coordinated system installations, testing and code corrections.
- Modified existing software systems to enhance performance and add new features.
- Communicated with and gathered feedback from customers about progress updates and worked to

- resolve specific concerns.
- Participated in team meetings and provided input on deadlines, designs and enhancements.
- Designed user-friendly software interfaces to simplify overall management.
- Identified issues in software processes and implemented optimization techniques resulting in 90% productivity increase.
- Designed mobile applications for Android platforms.

**Technologies**: Android, Kotlin, Python, Javascript, Motion, Java detection

#### Research Engineer

Swedish Veterinary Institute, Sweden

Nov 2018 - Dec 2018

#### Research Engineer

Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, Computational Biology and Bioinformatics, Sweden

Jul 2017 - Aug 2017

Designed and executed experiments, analyzed and interpreted primary data and formed logical conclusions. It resulted in a novel DNA alignment algorithm based on data reduction strategies.

**Technologies**: Python, SQLite, BLAST

- Directed complex engineering experiments to test, prove or modify theoretical propositions.
- Used advanced modeling capabilities to further product development processes.
- Designed and executed experiments, analyzed and interpreted primary data and formed logical conclusions.
- My work resulted in a highly automated pipeline with the purpose of screening toxicity

Technologies: Python, Anaconda, Autodock Vina

#### Freelance

Designed mobile applications for Apple and Android platforms,

Sweden

Technologies: Phonegap, HTML5, QR code libraries

Jan 2013 - Dec 2017

# Software Developer Consultant

HiForce, Sweden

Nov 2011 - Nov 2012

- Coordinated with project managers across multiple initiatives to align development timelines, plan testing and work with client representatives.
- Performed researched analysis to ascertain detailed client needs.
- Oversaw project schedules and evaluate progress toward important milestones at every phase of the project.
- Updated all stakeholders on key project milestones on

a monthly basis.

 Collaborated with product and engineering team members to define and develop new product concepts.

**Companies**: Swedish Church, Social Social Insurance Agency

**Technologies**: Java, WebLogic, HTML, Javascript, Visual Studio NET, SQL, XML, Windows PowerShell, NUnit, UML Rational Rose, XML, XSD, DOJO, JSON, WSDL, ANT, Eclipse, SCRUM, JMS, Spring Security, DB2, ClearCase, Python, Junit

#### R&D consultant

GenX Handelsbolag

March 2010 - Jun 2010

- Developed a navigation tool for the Ericcsson's base stations' networks
- Documented and showcased different key scenarios such as excel export/import and very large datasets

Technologies: Java, Java Swing, Eclipse

# Software Developer Consultant

Vilken Fibernet, Oslo, Norway

Nov 2008 - Feb 2009

- Worked on a more modern version of the client's CRM system
- Used unit testing in order to propose new functionality
- Performed testing, bug reporting and bug fixing

**Technologies**: Visual Studio NET 2008, Team Foundation Server, Silverlight, C#, Linq, XAML Expression Blend 2, NUnit

# Software Developer Consultant

Panopticon Software AB, Stockholm Sweden

Dec 2006 - May 2008

- Converted from C# to Java (Windows Forms to Java Swing) the client's Business Intelligence Visualization SDK.
- Further improved and added new functionalities to the converted SDK
- Early experimented on Vertica Database as AWS EC2
- Performed research and planning activities as part of an agile team

**Technologies**: Scrum, Vertica Database, .NET (C#), Windows Forms, Java Swing, Amazon Web Services.

### Developer and Architect Consultant

Casa Martinez AB, Stockholm, Sweden

Jun 2006 - Nov 2006

- Developed new functionality for the client's tableau system
- Searched and fixed bugs
- Periodically reported progress to the client.

Client: Sveriges Radio AB

**Technologies**: Visual Basic 6, Visual Studio NET, ASP NET, Progress, PL/SQL, VB Script, Java script, Web Services, XML, HTML

# Software Developer Consultant

Free Star technologies, Stockholm, Sweden

Jan 2005 - Jan 2006

- Worked on payment solution for online poker game
- Worked on fraud detection due to stolen credit cards.
- Daily reported directly to the directive about progress

Client: Rahaxi Processing Oy, Finland

**Technologies**: Visual Studio NET, ASP NET, MS SQL, MySQL, Netgiro API, TCP IP

# Software Developer Consultant

Interaktiv 3D Visualisering

Nov 2004 - Jan 2005

- Worked on the architecture, design and development of a tool to Stockholm's Moderna Museet 3D experience
- Developed website dedicated to CRM operations

Technologies: Lua, Quest3D, MySql, PHP

# Software Developer Consultant

Americas Software Corporation, Miami, USA

May 2003 - Jul 2004

- Developed web services for fraud detection in banking systems
- Supervised junior developers
- Developed installation and configuration systems

**Technologies**: Visual Studio NET, C#, Delphi, XML, Web services, Sharepoint web parts, Installshield api

# Software Developer Consultant

Modul1 Data AB, Stockholm, Sweden

Dec 2000 - March 2003

- Worked as full stack developer on SAS Resource Enterprise Planning System
- Supervised junior developers

Client: Scandinavian Airline Systems (SAS)

**Technologies:** UML, WebSphere Application Server (WAS), J2EE, Java SWING, C#

### **System Developer**

ABB Automation Product (Development Department, Division Control Center), Västerås, Sweden

Dec 1998 - Dec 1999

 Developed logical and visual components for object directory service of ABB's Advant family products

**Technologies:** Visual Studio 6.0, C++, VB, COM/DCOM, ATL, XML, Advant Controllers, Windows NT

## Software developer and tester

Commentor AB, Stockholm Sweden

Nov 1997 - March 1998

 Worked on development and improvement of the company's flagship product: TimeKey

 Worked on requirement compliance and implementation

**Technologies:** Borland C++, Sybase, Windows, Unix (HP)

# Software Developer Consultant

Flowinteractive AB, Stockholm Sweden

Jan 1999 - Jan 2000

- Worked on development of online casino
- Worked as architect and developer of business website (YesltWorks)
- Supervised junior developers

**Technologies:** Java, C, POSIX, TCP/IP sockets, J2EE, Leadership

#### Entrepreneur

Own company (Ferrer Soft Productions)

Oct 1994 - Aug 1997

### Research Engineer

IPK, Cuba

Dec 1992 - Dec 1993

- Developed computer game for kids
- Developed personal testing and profiling system for recruitment company

Technologies: Borland Delphi, SQL

 Research and Development in the subject of DNA analysis and epidemiology

Technologies: Visual Basic

### **Education and Training**

### Master degree student

Embedded systems, Uppsala University, Sweden Sep 2020 - Present

#### Master degree

Bioinformatics, Uppsala University, Sweden Sep 2015 - May 2019

#### Magister degree

Computer Science, Havana University, Cuba Sep 1986 - Jun 1992

Magister student Mechanical Engineering, CUJAE, Havana, Cuba Sep 1982 - Winter 1985

### Website

https://riemaxi.wordpress.com/